<rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" version="2.0"><channel><title>Matt's Stuff</title><description>Thoughts of a first year computer science student at UCL.</description><link>https://blog.mbell.me/</link><generator>Ghost 0.8</generator><lastBuildDate>Sat, 29 Oct 2016 02:43:55 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://blog.mbell.me/rss/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><ttl>60</ttl><item><title>Why I'm Voting To Stay In The EU</title><description>I know I said I wouldn't do this, but so what? Fight me.</description><link>https://blog.mbell.me/why-im-voting-to-stay-in-the-eu/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">6d8ec965-2ec4-4127-98e4-ad68ce1e8951</guid><category>politics</category><category>eww</category><dc:creator>Matthew Bell</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 21 May 2016 15:06:35 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="https://i.imgur.com/tznJgQP.jpg" medium="image"/><content:encoded>&lt;img src="https://i.imgur.com/tznJgQP.jpg" alt="Why I'm Voting To Stay In The EU"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Goddamn, people are not going to be quiet any time soon about this EU Referendum. But I mean, they do have a reason to. Whatever result we get, it's going to affect us (the young people) a lot more than it will affect older people, just for the fact that we'll be living and working for a longer time afterwards. So the clear thing I should say is that no matter what your view is, us under-30s &lt;em&gt;need&lt;/em&gt; to get out to the polling station and vote.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a rather slimy move by the government to put the polls on the 23rd June- it's the time of year when over 100,000 teens will descend upon Somerset for the Glastonbury Festival so they'll need to remember to apply for a postal vote by at least half a month before the referendum (if I remember rightly). Also, the end of June is typically when all us students will be coming back from university, just to complicate things further. I'm going to be out of London and away from home on my internship by that time, so I've had to apply for postal vote. Amongst all the confusion about where you'll be, perhaps this would be the best method for you. Regardless, &lt;strong&gt;your deadline is the 7th of June to register!&lt;/strong&gt; Find out more on the &lt;a href="http://www.aboutmyvote.co.uk/"&gt;About My Vote&lt;/a&gt; website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Okay, onto the meat of the discussion. I rather boldly decided to clearly say in this blog title how I'm voting, and I'm expecting a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; of flaming as a result of it. Oops, soz. I kinda have a bone to pick with the coverage though, the BBC and the government are meant to be two impartial entities, but they've been making a lot of pro-EU media stuff, and although I agree with that sentiment, surely they should be weighing up the advantages and disadvantages of both In and Out? There are proper lies being made by both camps though, and to be honest, &lt;strong&gt;no one has any idea what's going to happen&lt;/strong&gt;. Seriously, no one can time travel, and the success of an In vote or an Out vote depends entirely on 1) how our government handles it and 2) how other countries we trade with handle it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So at the world politics level, it's all about countries shit-talking others. But let's look at a more personal level. In three years, I'll hopefully wearing a graduation gown, holding a transcript for a degree from one of the most prestigious universities in the world (probably). As well as being able to apply for work in any UK tech firm, I'd also have the ability to look for work in any of the countries inside the EU, and I wouldn't need to mess around with some messy visa or green cards. Fantastic! However, it concerns me that I may not have this ability if we were to leave the EU. Also, what's not to say that tech companies up sticks from the UK? Even though that's speculation, it does worry me that the industry I'm training to work in may break down and move elsewhere because of the reduced connections.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As well, it's not just me that would suffer at university. Currently, 17% of undergraduates at UCL come from the EU (&lt;a href="https://www.ucl.ac.uk/srs/statistics"&gt;Source: UCL&lt;/a&gt;), and they're paying the same amount of tuition fees as UK students, which is £9000 per year. Non-EU students, for this course, will have to pay over £23,000 per year for the course, over twice as much! It saddens me to think that if we were to leave the EU, how many European students would turn down coming over here to study because of the excessively expensive degrees. But that's not all - our universities could potentially lose a collective one billion pounds in research funding if we leave the EU (&lt;a href="http://www.theregister.co.uk/2016/05/18/uk_unis_could_lose_1bn_in_funding_if_they_leave_the_eu/"&gt;Source: The Register&lt;/a&gt;), which would be crippling to the amount of research we do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So yeah, I know I'm probably going to get a lot of vitriolic comments over this blog post, but I thought it was best to get my opinion out there, because I care a lot about the future. I personally feel like leaving the EU is cutting off the nose to spite the face, but I digress. However you feel, please please please make sure you register, like, now, before it's too late. Bell OUT.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="//twitter.com/mbell_gb"&gt;@mbell_gb&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Run, Matt, Run!</title><description>You're all amazing, thank you so much for helping to beat heart disease.</description><link>https://blog.mbell.me/run-matt-run/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">e716adbe-b242-4c0e-a419-1b67d93bdcb9</guid><category>runmattrun</category><category>thanks</category><dc:creator>Matthew Bell</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 27 Mar 2016 16:17:13 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/tkXk8cpqo-cjfbUbvEPF1zp46EtWBL7Hzx8agzUS0OwHezIZAYNRlw053griWEZszKlX0lBhzty0ijiFMO05TPhQuc37vdwqdA4sUtVTIOf3DNDxn4C6AivP3aB2O-fzAAPr3W4oG6pjO68cMIeo1u6Fcd3KDFHExOt9fMHAW8twDWEbBWw9ZTb3dsgpn16NlttwAqQNV8-H_1ohTgk01tybx_56H_c0KTesGxsZ6zCdpGTxRrM2lCK7I2FT-zfSw9nmtanqT1n6JN4gso5nnjSrD0xM_3Xx2b6QXSlXi4-M-cNGqi46SQWOT1iPJ3PxzqDrgjK0FrJD1YXoyc0yQuPRJ5ggVJi9xO7utK60NaHagIyLmnbDN-BzgDRJxgufsBUOgTgL2UP8jvkYygWtU2OAdDmAwBVzpzgIiGVJWwCQGmgx2yrAjc0uh5Xie8skLpikb-23xZKNPUMf-YOIVew0udhYDLxvAAgG5dmdM72g5_4sSHRA25_RmT7wfosuHr3bfe6P3NgAyzoMhXqEKQmiw71rhWWiHtpoEuWb9G1yMyym8mr-lJSq9iOOWsK1J_49=w1242-h699-no" medium="image"/><content:encoded>&lt;img src="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/tkXk8cpqo-cjfbUbvEPF1zp46EtWBL7Hzx8agzUS0OwHezIZAYNRlw053griWEZszKlX0lBhzty0ijiFMO05TPhQuc37vdwqdA4sUtVTIOf3DNDxn4C6AivP3aB2O-fzAAPr3W4oG6pjO68cMIeo1u6Fcd3KDFHExOt9fMHAW8twDWEbBWw9ZTb3dsgpn16NlttwAqQNV8-H_1ohTgk01tybx_56H_c0KTesGxsZ6zCdpGTxRrM2lCK7I2FT-zfSw9nmtanqT1n6JN4gso5nnjSrD0xM_3Xx2b6QXSlXi4-M-cNGqi46SQWOT1iPJ3PxzqDrgjK0FrJD1YXoyc0yQuPRJ5ggVJi9xO7utK60NaHagIyLmnbDN-BzgDRJxgufsBUOgTgL2UP8jvkYygWtU2OAdDmAwBVzpzgIiGVJWwCQGmgx2yrAjc0uh5Xie8skLpikb-23xZKNPUMf-YOIVew0udhYDLxvAAgG5dmdM72g5_4sSHRA25_RmT7wfosuHr3bfe6P3NgAyzoMhXqEKQmiw71rhWWiHtpoEuWb9G1yMyym8mr-lJSq9iOOWsK1J_49=w1242-h699-no" alt="Run, Matt, Run!"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I woke up at 9:00 am yesterday morning, realising that in ninety minutes I had to be in Regent's Park to run a 5K. It wasn't something I really wanted to go and do, the bed was nice and cosy, my legs were still achey from training and it was kinda windy outside. However, somehow I ended up outside in the park with a bunch of people who were too enthusiastic for a Saturday morning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://blog.mbell.me/content/images/2016/03/run.png" alt="Run, Matt, Run!"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yada yada, the run happened and that's all good. Got a personal best time of 25 minutes 34 seconds as well, so that's always good. But the best thing was the money we raised together:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://blog.mbell.me/content/images/2016/03/run2.png" alt="Run, Matt, Run!"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That's an absolutely phenomenal amount, and I want to thank everyone personally who donated. As you may know, the British Heart Foundation is a charity which is close to my family and seeing the generosity of you lot makes me a lot less cynical about the world, and also makes the incredible pain I'm in this morning all the more worth it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks again,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/mbell_gb"&gt;Matt&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>That NPM Situation</title><description>&lt;p&gt;For a few hours overnight, there was utter panic in the Node.js community. &lt;a href="https://www.npmjs.com/package/left-pad"&gt;left-pad&lt;/a&gt;, a package that consists of an eleven-line JS file, was unpublished from the Node Package Manager registry. You may think that this is a minor thing, but certain packages depended on left-pad. And certain, very&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>https://blog.mbell.me/that-npm-situation/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">403dcb66-4cf0-4b8a-a70d-305fdb39b6de</guid><category>node.js</category><category>web dev</category><category>Drama</category><dc:creator>Matthew Bell</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 23 Mar 2016 17:03:10 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="https://blog.mbell.me/content/images/2016/03/colors.jpg" medium="image"/><content:encoded>&lt;img src="https://blog.mbell.me/content/images/2016/03/colors.jpg" alt="That NPM Situation"&gt;&lt;p&gt;For a few hours overnight, there was utter panic in the Node.js community. &lt;a href="https://www.npmjs.com/package/left-pad"&gt;left-pad&lt;/a&gt;, a package that consists of an eleven-line JS file, was unpublished from the Node Package Manager registry. You may think that this is a minor thing, but certain packages depended on left-pad. And certain, very popular packages depended on those. The result was broken builds, broken builds &lt;a href="http://www.theregister.co.uk/2016/03/23/npm_left_pad_chaos/"&gt;everywhere&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So this actually brings up a whole bunch of big questions for the JavaScript community. The first of those being, why did the maintainer remove all of their packages from NPM? The chap in question, Azer Koçulu, wrote a very interesting and thought provoking Medium &lt;a href="https://medium.com/@azerbike/i-ve-just-liberated-my-modules-9045c06be67c#.1huqy7a1m"&gt;article&lt;/a&gt;, stating that he believes that "NPM is someone’s private land where corporate is more powerful than the people" due to actions over a copyright claim. He also goes on to say that his code is still available on GitHub and he believes in open source. So really, although he &lt;em&gt;did&lt;/em&gt; break a lot of people's projects, you gotta respect his integrity, right? It's something he did in the name of Open Source, and you can't really argue against that (although, I imagine that it wasn't the easiest decision to make).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, it brings up yet more moral dilemmas for awful tech commentators (both casual, like me, and professional, like not-me). Hours after left-pad was removed, the CTO of NPM, Laurie Voss, stepped in and added left-pad back to the registry himself, in what he described as an 'unprecedented' action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;Hey npm users: left-pad 0.0.3 was unpublished, breaking LOTS of builds. To fix, we are un-un-publishing it at the request of the new owner.&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Laurie Voss (@seldo) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/seldo/status/712414400808755200"&gt;March 22, 2016&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;  

&lt;script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And again, you may count it as a 'wrong' action, but it's deciding between whether to support millions of projects or support one guy. And in this case they went with the former. And in NPM's defence again, left-pad was released under the WTFPL, which reads as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;DO WHAT THE F**K YOU WANT TO PUBLIC LICENSE 
  Version 2, December 2004
  Copyright (C) 2004 Sam Hocevar &lt;a href="https://blog.mbell.me/that-npm-situation/&amp;#109;&amp;#x61;&amp;#x69;&amp;#108;&amp;#x74;&amp;#x6f;:&amp;#x73;&amp;#97;&amp;#x6d;&amp;#x40;&amp;#x68;&amp;#111;&amp;#99;&amp;#101;&amp;#118;&amp;#x61;r&amp;#46;&amp;#x6e;&amp;#101;t"&gt;&amp;#x73;&amp;#97;&amp;#x6d;&amp;#x40;&amp;#x68;&amp;#111;&amp;#99;&amp;#101;&amp;#118;&amp;#x61;r&amp;#46;&amp;#x6e;&amp;#101;t&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;Everyone is permitted to copy and distribute verbatim or modified copies of this license document, and changing it is allowed as long as the name is changed.&lt;/p&gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;DO WHAT THE F**K YOU WANT TO PUBLIC LICENSE 
  TERMS AND CONDITIONS FOR COPYING, DISTRIBUTION AND MODIFICATION&lt;/p&gt;
  
  &lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You just DO WHAT THE F**K YOU WANT TO.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, I guess they can kinda 'do what the f**k' they want to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id="therestofthedominosfalllikeahouseofcardscheckmate"&gt;...the rest of the dominos fall like a house of cards. Checkmate.&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another big question we should be looking at is, why should a user removing one package containing eleven lines of code break thousands of projects, builds and other packages? It exploits a huge flaw with NPM that should ideally be addressed. Perhaps rather than code being deleted, it is 'archived' and cannot be viewed on the registry any more, while still being able to be accessed by packages that use it already. Or perhaps the entry should be orphaned, for someone else to take on; since packages have open source licenses, it should easily allow other maintainers to take over.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or perhaps, the whole model is wrong. Look at Linux distributions; their package managers tend to let you add/remove repositories, or servers where be packages. For instance, Arch Linux has &lt;code&gt;core&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;extra&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;community&lt;/code&gt; repositories amongst others, but there is no stopping me, a user, from adding the custom &lt;code&gt;infinality&lt;/code&gt; repository, which isn't owned by Arch Linux but provides binary files of the infinality font program. &lt;strong&gt;As far as I know&lt;/strong&gt; this is not possible with &lt;code&gt;npm&lt;/code&gt;, the command line tool for the registry; that you can only choose one registry in the config file. It seems like you need to depend on &lt;em&gt;extra&lt;/em&gt; tools to get the ability to use many registries at the same time, for instance &lt;a href="https://strongloop.com/strongblog/switch-between-configure-public-and-private-npm-registry/"&gt;StrongLoop&lt;/a&gt;. Or at least it's currently something set in the &lt;code&gt;package.json&lt;/code&gt; file, something discussed in NPM issue &lt;a href="https://github.com/npm/npm/issues/1401"&gt;#1401&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To conclude, there are some &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; pertinent issues with Node.js and NPM right now, but it seems like that until a truly open source competitor is created (and is adopted to the same level), we need to make steps to make do with what we've got. Comments are very much appreciated below if you have views and/or corrections, and I'm also interested in your views on Twitter too - my username is &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/mbell_gb"&gt;@mbell_gb&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>I Did A Stupid.</title><description>Sometimes you gotta break a few omelettes to make an egg. Wait, what?</description><link>https://blog.mbell.me/i-did-a-stupid/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">7ebab94c-1453-477d-9f28-3fcf4888a19f</guid><category>web dev</category><category>node.js</category><dc:creator>Matthew Bell</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 07 Mar 2016 10:04:04 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="https://blog.mbell.me/content/images/2016/03/2016-02-23_011744_scrot.png" medium="image"/><content:encoded>&lt;img src="https://blog.mbell.me/content/images/2016/03/2016-02-23_011744_scrot.png" alt="I Did A Stupid."&gt;&lt;p&gt;So last night, you may or may not have noticed that &lt;a href="//mbell.me"&gt;mbell.me&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="//blog.mbell.me"&gt;blog.mbell.me&lt;/a&gt; were unavailable and couldn't be reached. Why? Well, I did a bad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;Hey, y&amp;#39;all. mbell.me is currently down due to a server problem (the problem being me)&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Matt (@mbell_gb) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/mbell_gb/status/706653817002139648"&gt;March 7, 2016&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;  

&lt;script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, what went wrong? I was in the middle of a routine upgrade of Ghost, the blogging platform I use. I needed to move the new server files to my 'live', or &lt;code&gt;www&lt;/code&gt; folder as I know it. So far, so good. But then I start running into problems. Missing npm dependencies were found, which is odd considering that literally nothing has changed on my setup. But anyway, I carry on through and get round to cleaning up the upgrade files. I needed to chown the ghost directory to my app user, but instead, I fat-fingered it and instead of typing:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;# chown -R ./ ghost:ghost
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I typed:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;# chown -R / ghost:ghost
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bad stuff happened. &lt;code&gt;sudo&lt;/code&gt; no longer worked. In fact, not a lot of things were still working. My homepage was still up through, graced by the fact that it doesn't need to be modified once online. So I had to take the decision of restarting the virtual machine from scratch. Luckily, I had a mid-February backup, so most of the blog is back -- save for the images.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id="howtosaveyourserverfromyou"&gt;How to save your server from you&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It's no secret that server management and backend operations are the stuff of hatred for most people working with the web. But honestly, by learning now you'll be exploring how to avoid doing stupid things on your server (like chowning the root directory). Below are a couple of tips I'd like to share, as well as links to some great resources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Each app has its own user.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When creating a new webapp on your server, you should really create a new system user dedicated for &lt;strong&gt;just&lt;/strong&gt; that app. It means that you can allow someone (who is trusted) to access that app with SSH key entry without having access to the rest of your server. It also means that if that app were to become compromised for whatever reason, the damage can be mitigated and not be extended to, say, your home page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Use bare Git repositories rather than making a repository in your web directory.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seeing as this is the production server, you need to use a bare Git repository rather than your standard working Git repository, because you are not going to work directly on the server. A lot of people have explained the difference of what bare repositories are, I'll link them at the end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Use nvm to control your node.js versions.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;nvm&lt;/code&gt; is the Node.js Version Manager; it's an unofficial tool that lets you explicitly choose a version of Node.js to use. I think very highly of it, as it means that you're not going to have as many problems of "x not supported in version y" or whatever. It's also installed per-user as well, so no sudo access is required for installing node or for installing global npm packages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="linksandstuff"&gt;Links and stuff&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.gitguys.com/topics/shared-repositories-should-be-bare-repositories/"&gt;Gitguys - Shared Repositories Should Be Bare Repositories&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.saintsjd.com/2011/01/what-is-a-bare-git-repository/"&gt;Jon Saints - What is a bare Git repository?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.digitalocean.com/community/tutorials"&gt;DigitalOcean Tutorials&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>HackLondon, The Bestest Hackathon In The Bestest City?</title><description>HackLondon was a pure example of how to do a hackathon right. Thanks you guys!</description><link>https://blog.mbell.me/hacklondon-the-bestest-hackathon-in-the-bestest-city/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">6fe5e9b0-81c8-4c2e-ba6f-e104e2309d07</guid><category>hackathons</category><category>Programming</category><dc:creator>Matthew Bell</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 29 Feb 2016 19:28:00 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/Xp8d5B4SugQuvYGrHBWQWb2F-W8_uVYVwypDVyIOeZUZxNYI_jjHJTqH1dz31y69NslveX5tJYQIwtn9MBEXPebPMOqn8ppCSTyuqI-2H40r4bfdHM_Vic_33tukUWAhov6VhPFcpvW6FPcjN3jBJDsIEYkw4XOKFFv4Clz-W_S8uQgcq5nMjWaZwOCDiMrurGVHqvQ1xxb6WH2bNvHXfFPwXdtq_jRiUu3dWFY92gt7BHA92tZRKTEg_I0Ly0CON8SaAGningXyCig6U8FlnaEb7qn2f-tq3HP2ynQ7YFHBbigM839QEq6i6MbPthixtMQFVVoRUqFof4dgsNjgTHkAmDVpy-c1C3dLzj6XITTyOtg7DOjScLcj0DEhwkYTbdaZTMw8y_jkkw9iMY7vQ3q318BlmQ98WwkEo8CiQPP4mIZV4oc__8t5w-koLSBLHhNULt6BJxZhnzQ9QoShWFPeO8PMLKVREN8IJTIZra23WD5F56W-mIg0nKoynqVRf_G5hRT6XbyzeqpXp88NgkOlo0C8q903r3tRQNoB5NFe6ZxFRiWLfLyms1gt3ELNKJ-6=w2000-h1400-no" medium="image"/><content:encoded>&lt;img src="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/Xp8d5B4SugQuvYGrHBWQWb2F-W8_uVYVwypDVyIOeZUZxNYI_jjHJTqH1dz31y69NslveX5tJYQIwtn9MBEXPebPMOqn8ppCSTyuqI-2H40r4bfdHM_Vic_33tukUWAhov6VhPFcpvW6FPcjN3jBJDsIEYkw4XOKFFv4Clz-W_S8uQgcq5nMjWaZwOCDiMrurGVHqvQ1xxb6WH2bNvHXfFPwXdtq_jRiUu3dWFY92gt7BHA92tZRKTEg_I0Ly0CON8SaAGningXyCig6U8FlnaEb7qn2f-tq3HP2ynQ7YFHBbigM839QEq6i6MbPthixtMQFVVoRUqFof4dgsNjgTHkAmDVpy-c1C3dLzj6XITTyOtg7DOjScLcj0DEhwkYTbdaZTMw8y_jkkw9iMY7vQ3q318BlmQ98WwkEo8CiQPP4mIZV4oc__8t5w-koLSBLHhNULt6BJxZhnzQ9QoShWFPeO8PMLKVREN8IJTIZra23WD5F56W-mIg0nKoynqVRf_G5hRT6XbyzeqpXp88NgkOlo0C8q903r3tRQNoB5NFe6ZxFRiWLfLyms1gt3ELNKJ-6=w2000-h1400-no" alt="HackLondon, The Bestest Hackathon In The Bestest City?"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This last weekend, two hundred eager hackers (me being one of them) descended upon University College London's North and South Cloisters to build, program and hack entertaining, interesting and overall very cool things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In our team, we created a Git automation tool which we called Git++ (&lt;a href="https://github.com/jakerockland/git-plus-leap"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://devpost.com/software/git-plus-leap"&gt;devpost&lt;/a&gt;). What did it do, you may ask? We forked the very popular git-plus package for Atom, and relentlessly hacked it to provide gesture control using the LEAP Motion controller - swipe upwards with your hand to commit your changes, swipe left to pull from your remote, and swipe right to push. It was a lot of fun to play with, and not so fun to develop (Sleep? What's that?), but it was the first hackathon project I've actually managed to complete, so I'm incredibly proud of what we've done! Also, we have a demo on &lt;a href="https://www.periscope.tv/w/aaLj8zIzNjAzMzZ8MW5BSkVsYWt3eW9HTP0AFce9Err9gVY3zIdjDkNwY28Y5lpQ-Pn6LiJb6lB8"&gt;Periscope&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was definitely a novelty in hacking in the place you visit every day, but that sadly wore off when I realised that I'd be seeing the same place again on Monday. Such is life. It's interesting to note that the lecture theatre where we have theory lectures was used for filming in the film Inception (shout out to my man Leo Dicaps).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It's probably worth at this point giving a shout out to the legendary volunteers from UCL Tech Soc (the baes) and KCL Tech for actually making this event happen, as well as the team from MLH for also helping to support the event, as well of course the sponsors who basically pay for it all. Also, thanks to other hackers who came over to help us with a couple of bits, in return for us coming over and helping them with stuff. That's what makes hackathons so special.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, I should go back to bed. Ten hours of sleep for the whole weekend does not a happy Matthew make.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;P.S. I'll post the results of the sleep survey as soon as possible!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class="instagram-media" data-instgrm-captioned="" data-instgrm-version="6" style=" background:#FFF; border:0; border-radius:3px; box-shadow:0 0 1px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.5),0 1px 10px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.15); margin: 1px; max-width:658px; padding:0; width:99.375%; width:-webkit-calc(100% - 2px); width:calc(100% - 2px);"&gt;&lt;div style="padding:8px;"&gt; &lt;div style=" background:#F8F8F8; line-height:0; margin-top:40px; padding:50.0% 0; text-align:center; width:100%;"&gt; &lt;div style=" background:url(data:image/png;base64,iVBORw0KGgoAAAANSUhEUgAAACwAAAAsCAMAAAApWqozAAAAGFBMVEUiIiI9PT0eHh4gIB4hIBkcHBwcHBwcHBydr+JQAAAACHRSTlMABA4YHyQsM5jtaMwAAADfSURBVDjL7ZVBEgMhCAQBAf//42xcNbpAqakcM0ftUmFAAIBE81IqBJdS3lS6zs3bIpB9WED3YYXFPmHRfT8sgyrCP1x8uEUxLMzNWElFOYCV6mHWWwMzdPEKHlhLw7NWJqkHc4uIZphavDzA2JPzUDsBZziNae2S6owH8xPmX8G7zzgKEOPUoYHvGz1TBCxMkd3kwNVbU0gKHkx+iZILf77IofhrY1nYFnB/lQPb79drWOyJVa/DAvg9B/rLB4cC+Nqgdz/TvBbBnr6GBReqn/nRmDgaQEej7WhonozjF+Y2I/fZou/qAAAAAElFTkSuQmCC); display:block; height:44px; margin:0 auto -44px; position:relative; top:-22px; width:44px;"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt; &lt;p style=" margin:8px 0 0 0; padding:0 4px;"&gt; &lt;a href="https://www.instagram.com/p/BCVddAuQMEH/" style=" color:#000; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; font-style:normal; font-weight:normal; line-height:17px; text-decoration:none; word-wrap:break-word;" target="_blank"&gt;Second finalist: Git++ #hacklondon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p style=" color:#c9c8cd; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; line-height:17px; margin-bottom:0; margin-top:8px; overflow:hidden; padding:8px 0 7px; text-align:center; text-overflow:ellipsis; white-space:nowrap;"&gt;A photo posted by Hack London (@hacklondon) on &lt;time style=" font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; line-height:17px;" datetime="2016-02-28T15:40:27+00:00"&gt;Feb 28, 2016 at 7:40am PST&lt;/time&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;  

&lt;script async defer src="//platform.instagram.com/en_US/embeds.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Hey, Look At That, I'm An Android User Now</title><description>So long Windows Phone, I don't need you any more: Android is good again.</description><link>https://blog.mbell.me/hey-look-at-that-im-an-android-user-now/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">da47ced6-0f1f-45a5-af55-1ee84ca64e1e</guid><dc:creator>Matthew Bell</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 14 Feb 2016 01:09:45 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="https://blog.mbell.me/content/images/2016/06/IrFMpUu.jpg" medium="image"/><content:encoded>&lt;img src="https://blog.mbell.me/content/images/2016/06/IrFMpUu.jpg" alt="Hey, Look At That, I'm An Android User Now"&gt;&lt;p&gt;About four years ago, I was in the market for my next phone. I was after something mid-range, good value, a decent camera, and above all, a good OS. I was instantly wowed by the Windows Phone 7's inky black, silky smooth interface, and picked up a Nokia Lumia 800, rather than pick an average Android device. Android at the time was not very smooth to use on a lot of devices, and most manufacturers liked to add tonnes of bloatware onto their devices (the old TouchWiz being the most infamous of them all).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Windows Phone 7 users got a bit shafted though, when we found out that we wouldn't be getting an upgrade to Windows Phone 8. At this point my contract was due again. Should I pick a budget-to-midrange Android device, or Lumia 1020 which was being offered to me at a deal? I picked Windows again (for worse perhaps), since I wasn't that content with using a half-arsed low spec Samsung. The phone ran okay for most of the time, but since late last year started developing problems and even led me to missing lectures and &lt;a href="https://blog.matthewb.me/windows-phone-is-broken-and-probably-dead/"&gt;other things&lt;/a&gt;. So, a couple of weeks ago, I decided to give Android a proper chance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I picked up the Motorola Moto G (3rd Generation) during a sale for £89 (RRP is £149), which was an absolute &lt;em&gt;steal&lt;/em&gt;. It came with Android Lollipop (5.1) and has totally blown me away with how smooth the operating system has become. Even though the device is a &lt;em&gt;tad&lt;/em&gt; underpowered (Snapdragon 410 and 1 GB RAM, anyone?), it can still run most things with ease and performs sublimely for what I was going to consider as a stop-gap phone to my next contract. The device feels excellent to hold, and the display is nice and bright - although it's "only" a 1280x720 pixel resolution. The battery life also lasts me a day, a far cry from the Lumia where I had to semi-permanently attach a USB cable to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://blog.mbell.me/content/images/2016/06/Moto_G_Black_Front_Underwater.jpg" alt="Hey, Look At That, I'm An Android User Now"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My only issues with the device so far is the lack of storage; the Moto G only has 8 GB of onboard memory and this is half consumed by Android itself, not leaving you with loads of room. Luckily, it does have a MicroSD card slot (also something new for me as Windows Phone never used to support this) so the memory is expandable by up to 32 GB I believe. Also, the Moto G &lt;em&gt;does&lt;/em&gt; lack an NFC chip, although this isn't really an issue for me as most of the time it's just a battery drain and a nuisance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Droid on! &lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href="//twitter.com/mbell_gb"&gt;@mbell_gb&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Windows Phone Is Broken And Probably Dead</title><description>Sorry Windows, all the FUD you can create will not help you now. My time with you is up after four years of hope.</description><link>https://blog.mbell.me/windows-phone-is-broken-and-probably-dead/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">2f3ed146-4f5e-4a9b-bb41-a70ba64091d6</guid><category>windows phone</category><category>rant</category><dc:creator>Matthew Bell</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 01 Feb 2016 10:45:09 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="https://blog.mbell.me/content/images/2016/06/WP_20140429_20_04_24_Pro.jpg" medium="image"/><content:encoded>&lt;img src="https://blog.mbell.me/content/images/2016/06/WP_20140429_20_04_24_Pro.jpg" alt="Windows Phone Is Broken And Probably Dead"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I'm writing this from a coffee shop, rather than the nine o'clock lecture I'm meant to be in. Why? Because my phone didn't activate the alarms I set... again. This time it was because my phone was on silent mode. Really?! I set my phone to silent so that I wouldn't get disturbed by notifications in the night, and it muted the alarm too? A different problem happened on Saturday. I slept through my alarm and missed my very early train because it just so happened that Windows assumed that I "would not be busy" at that time and started applying a phone update.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It definitely seems like Windows Mobile 10 For Phones (the proper name for it) is two steps forwards, and a 100m sprint backwards for the underdog phone OS. Yes, I understand that as this is an 'insider preview', things should be broken, so why has Microsoft assumed that it is okay to preload their new phones with this build? You'd thing that if they were using it in production devices, then it'd be stable enough to use day to day. Right? It's worth noting before I get too ranty, that I have been using Windows Phone for four years now. I got shafted when Microsoft announced that WP7 devices would not be getting an upgrade to WP8, but I still got a Windows Phone 8 device mainly because of the extreme camera and good design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the most part, it is. I mean, if you can deal with the waiting. Seriously. Boot time has rocketed to about three or four minutes, and I think I spend most of my time on the device waiting for a "loading..." or "resuming..." screen to finish. Navigation is a joke and the phone frequently has problems acquiring a connection to GPS satellites. Spotify is unusable, and songs will literally just stop playing at random, as well as slowly consuming more and more of your devices limited storage. The Twitter app still lives in 2013, and the Instagram app actually hasn't been updated since 2013 (luckily, there's a third party app that is a whole order of magnitude better. 6tag is the name). Snapchat? Yik Yak? Your bank? Good luck finding them on the Windows Store. Unless you're banking with Barclays, who have a very well developed Windows app.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Microsoft were betting on Windows 10 attracting more developers to the platform by introducing the idea of Universal Windows Platform (UWP) - that all Windows 10 devices could be targeted using the exact same code. They hoped that developers and app makers would be tempted to tap into the massive market of desktop users and then created mobile apps as a result, but the truth is that for most computer users, you're probably going to just use your web browser. Also, Windows' market share is steadily being shrunk by the dominance of Apple and OSX. As much as it pains me to say, I would probably prefer to use a Mac because if you scrape away the Fischer Price interface, you actually have a UNIX system, which in my eyes earns it mad nerd cred. Even GNU/Linux is only UNIX-like, which means that it is essentially just like UNIX in most use cases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, I hate to say it Windows, but with your flailing mobile ecosystem and quickly vanishing desktop market share, you're dead son.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Bullet Journal, One Month Later</title><description>Does the bullet journal system make you a more organised person, or is it pointless?</description><link>https://blog.mbell.me/bullet-journal-one-month-on/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">80935843-f50d-4742-b2dc-8992e1ac2b7f</guid><category>bullet journal</category><category>review</category><dc:creator>Matthew Bell</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 28 Jan 2016 18:02:41 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="https://blog.mbell.me/content/images/2016/06/WP_20160128_17_54_37_Pro.jpg" medium="image"/><content:encoded>&lt;img src="https://blog.mbell.me/content/images/2016/06/WP_20160128_17_54_37_Pro.jpg" alt="Bullet Journal, One Month Later"&gt;&lt;p&gt;At the start of the month, &lt;a href="https://blog.matthewb.me/lets-get-organised/"&gt;I made a Bullet Journal&lt;/a&gt; (more information &lt;a href="//bulletjournal.com/get-started/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;) and have been using it since. The premise has been reasonably simple. Need to remember something or make a task? It goes into the journal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="amimoreorganised"&gt;Am I More Organised?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Uh... no.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem is, whilst the bullet journal is nice to put notes and things in, there needs to be work on your side too. I keep slipping into the habit of making mental reminders rather than writing it down somewhere, so perhaps it'll just take some getting used to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="ialreadyusecortanasirigooglenowhowdoesthisstackup"&gt;I already use Cortana/Siri/Google Now. How does this stack up?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I own a Windows Phone, which comes with the Cortana virtual assistant. I like it a lot, and it does automate a lot of things like setting reminders based on location or person, rather than a time (for instance, "remind me when I'm at the supermarket", "remind me next time I get a phone call from Grandma"). However, it does feel a little intrusive, especially as it can be set to trawl your emails for &lt;a href="https://www.windowsphone.com/en-us/how-to/wp8/cortana/cortanas-settings?signin=true"&gt;flight tickets&lt;/a&gt; or parcel tracking numbers. It's pretty neat, but a tad creepy. A notebook doesn't do any of this, you only share with it what you write in it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, a notebook is cross platform.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>A more SASSy blog theme</title><description>The blog got a new makeover, finally it matches the rest of the site! I make a blog post to commemorate this.</description><link>https://blog.mbell.me/a-more-sassy-blog-theme/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">0a33adb3-a6fc-4dc3-a01c-04c665668463</guid><category>blog</category><category>Meta</category><category>web dev</category><dc:creator>Matthew Bell</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 25 Jan 2016 20:36:51 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="https://blog.mbell.me/content/images/2016/06/WP_20140511_20_45_36_ev1_Pro.jpg" medium="image"/><content:encoded>&lt;img src="https://blog.mbell.me/content/images/2016/06/WP_20140511_20_45_36_ev1_Pro.jpg" alt="A more SASSy blog theme"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I'm not going to lie, this theme took about a day to make. It's basically just my website theme with a couple of new classes and then a few handlebar files to make the templates. Of course, because it only took a day to make there's going to be bugs. If something looks broken or doesn't work properly, make a new issue &lt;a href="https://github.com/logicnotlogical/ghost-mbell/issues"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and make sure to put your OS + browser version and I will be very grateful!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="sassmakescssliterally100xbetter"&gt;Sass makes CSS literally 100x better.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://blog.mbell.me/content/images/2016/06/2016-01-25_202329_scrot.png" alt="A more SASSy blog theme"&gt;
The problem with CSS is that it can get a little bit... messy. Thankfully, there are a bunch of frameworks which aim to improve this, the two most known ones are Sass and LESS - as you can see, I chose Sass for reasons. These languages are compiled, or 'pre processed' into standard CSS files that can be used on the web. The languages come with a bunch of extra features you don't get in CSS like inheritance, variables and functions. My site would be literally impossible to make without one of these used, honestly. The best bit is that the turquoise colour is set as a variable, so one line of text can make my site absolutely hideous.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="youtoocanusethistheme"&gt;You too can use this theme&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I put the source files on GitHub and are released, as usual, under the &lt;a href="https://opensource.org/licenses/MIT"&gt;MIT License&lt;/a&gt;. Essentially: do what you want with the code, I'd love it if you reference me in your project though! Oh, also, the code is provided as-is so don't come crying to me if you pushed it to production and things broke.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/logicnotlogical" class="button"&gt;&lt;i class="fa fa-github"&gt;&lt;/i&gt; GitHub Repository&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Hackathon Ideas</title><description>Some ideas for hackathons.</description><link>https://blog.mbell.me/hackathon-ideas/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">34825368-3536-4bc7-b055-ad0e440f33d3</guid><category>hackathons</category><category>misc</category><dc:creator>Matthew Bell</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 24 Jan 2016 19:03:36 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="https://blog.mbell.me/content/images/2016/06/hack.jpg" medium="image"/><content:encoded>&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tinder for dogs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Facebook Roulette. Press the button and the app will like a random photo of a random friend. Depending on how old the photo is, the ramifications could be rather extreme.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A watch that screams to wake you up&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A coffee machine that makes you complete a maths puzzle to access the coffee.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A robot that fetches your phone.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A door that opens if you say, "this is a robbery!"&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A sarcastic kettle&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A cold iron&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An app that uses the Clarifai vision API to pick the most horrifying image possible&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A reverse phone charger&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A wifi-enabled mug&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Twitter for people&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A VR-based driving test practice&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Node.js implemented with Haskell&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Let's Get Organised</title><description>I find about about the "bullet journal". Goes as expected.</description><link>https://blog.mbell.me/lets-get-organised/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">bb57bfb3-a04f-4ab8-9dda-df08cff2b6fc</guid><category>bullet journal</category><category>organisation</category><dc:creator>Matthew Bell</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 02 Jan 2016 20:03:39 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="https://blog.mbell.me/content/images/2016/06/WP_20160102_20_00_34_Pro.jpg" medium="image"/><content:encoded>&lt;img src="https://blog.mbell.me/content/images/2016/06/WP_20160102_20_00_34_Pro.jpg" alt="Let's Get Organised"&gt;&lt;p&gt;So, this one's pretty cool. I read on Lifehacker about a new way of keeping a to-do list in a notebook/journal, which is called the &lt;a href="http://bulletjournal.com/"&gt;Bullet Journal&lt;/a&gt;. You may think that's kinda weird for a computer science student to write stuff down in a book but it seems like a really neat way of journaling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You put stuff you want to do months in advance in the "future log", for instance that task you haven't quite got around to doing yet but is not critically urgent. Stuff you're planning for the month goes into the "monthly log", for instance appointments, holidays, and birthdays et cetera. Finally, stuff you have planned for the day goes into the "daily log" as it comes up. Things like talking to someone about a feature, picking something up from the shops, or any other similar stuff. The system seems pretty rigid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The proof's in the pudding, right? We'll see how it all goes in the next few months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="//twitter.com/mbell_gb"&gt;@mbell_gb&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>2015, ciao.</title><description>A look back at a pretty good year, with many pictures and things to go with it.</description><link>https://blog.mbell.me/2015-ciao/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">7fe797d7-74ad-4129-aae7-9ebd12d253b9</guid><category>2015</category><category>pictures</category><category>me</category><dc:creator>Matthew Bell</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 31 Dec 2015 22:26:00 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="https://blog.mbell.me/content/images/2016/06/nice.jpg" medium="image"/><content:encoded>&lt;img src="https://blog.mbell.me/content/images/2016/06/nice.jpg" alt="2015, ciao."&gt;&lt;p&gt;It's not just me, is it? As I sit here, sipping some badly made cocktails (I can't make an El Dorado to save my life), I can't ignore the fact that this year has gone really, really quickly. This time last year I remember thinking to myself that the next twelve months could either go pretty well or horribly wrong, and thankfully it's gone pretty well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;January was spent being grumpy that I didn't get a UCAS offer for Oxford, although I was incredibly happy that I got an offer from UCL. Maybe it was just winter blues. Who knows. I was also in the middle of my computing final project, so I had just spent that Christmas doing UI implementations and unit testing. I did get a fantastic new laptop to program and hack on, so I was occupied in a good way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;February was a pretty forgetful month, as did March. I think that the fact that they are both cold, and the fact that February is short, that we try and forget about them as much as possible. Do you know many people with a birthday in February? Thought not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People remember April though because that's when you have to do tax things by. You come out of hibernation on the first of April and the weather is normally starting to get less Siberian by then as well. I for one had the 200 page "project report" to work through, as well as countless maths exercises on complex numbers, multivariate calculus and other stuff that may come in useful at &lt;em&gt;some&lt;/em&gt; point in the future... right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;May is short for "Mayday!", because that's what you'll be shouting when you realise that your exams begin this month. I had completed about one tree's worth of past exam papers during that month, and also had my final lessons. We had some pretty amazing selfies taken:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://blog.mbell.me/content/images/2016/06/comp.jpg" alt="2015, ciao."&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://blog.mbell.me/content/images/2016/06/11103199_896570620400979_6390615549916310934_o.jpg" alt="2015, ciao."&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had the displeasure of having the last exam in college, COMP3, but then had the actual pleasure of flying to Gran Canaria with some of my besties just two days later. Sadly I didn't get the window seat on the flight out, but trivial physics never stop me:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://blog.mbell.me/content/images/2016/06/plane.jpg" alt="2015, ciao."&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gran Canaria was fantastic, would definitely come back again in the future. But since I am not a travel blog, I shall only show photos. (Wait, what kind of blog even is this?)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://blog.mbell.me/content/images/2016/06/beach.jpg" alt="2015, ciao."&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://blog.mbell.me/content/images/2016/06/people.jpg" alt="2015, ciao."&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What happened in July? Not a lot to be honest, there was a lot of worrying and fretting over what was to come over the next couple of months...&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I finally got to see my fate in August, when the A-level results were released. I didn't sleep a &lt;em&gt;wink&lt;/em&gt; the night before, so I was too tired, worried and hungry. Thankfully my results were &lt;strong&gt;more&lt;/strong&gt; that what I wanted (hence why I'm at UCL now!) I also found out that my computing result was in the top 50 in the &lt;strong&gt;whole&lt;/strong&gt; country which I was ecstatic about! Unless I was 50/50. But they never said so it's okay. Maybe the lure of the holiday encouraged me in the exam? Maybe it was sheer luck? Who knows, it's over now. It meant that I got the chance to visit the offices of Netcraft, an web security service, and get a rather durable rucksack from them - the first of many pieces of company swag I would come to accumulate during my time as a student. Oh, and &lt;a href="//mbell.me"&gt;matthewb.me (now mbell.me)&lt;/a&gt; finally got registered as my domain name.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Time ticked oh so very fast round to September, which was massive for me for two reasons. The first was that I was moving into the city, which is pretty scary if you've been living in a village for most of your life. Thankfully, I've met so many lovely people both on my corridor and in my course so I definitely feel like I've made the right choice in coming here. Even if I do still miss my old friends (if you are reading this, drinks?)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://blog.mbell.me/content/images/2016/06/tube.jpg" alt="2015, ciao."&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh, also I finally got to see Foo Fighters live. A pretty outstanding few hours considering that I've been listening to Dave Grohl's voice from the cradle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://blog.mbell.me/content/images/2016/06/dave.jpg" alt="2015, ciao."&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In October, I experienced my first ever hackathon and I'm now a little bit hooked. Making things is fun! Additionally, Me and a couple of people from my course went to Facebook headquarters to win a competition (well, second place but we won prizes so there). Hacking is fun! Oh, and also I went veggie during this month (and still am).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class="instagram-media" data-instgrm-captioned="" data-instgrm-version="6" style=" background:#FFF; border:0; border-radius:3px; box-shadow:0 0 1px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.5),0 1px 10px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.15); margin: 1px; max-width:658px; padding:0; width:99.375%; width:-webkit-calc(100% - 2px); width:calc(100% - 2px);"&gt;&lt;div style="padding:8px;"&gt; &lt;div style=" background:#F8F8F8; line-height:0; margin-top:40px; padding:50.0% 0; text-align:center; width:100%;"&gt; &lt;div style=" background:url(data:image/png;base64,iVBORw0KGgoAAAANSUhEUgAAACwAAAAsCAMAAAApWqozAAAAGFBMVEUiIiI9PT0eHh4gIB4hIBkcHBwcHBwcHBydr+JQAAAACHRSTlMABA4YHyQsM5jtaMwAAADfSURBVDjL7ZVBEgMhCAQBAf//42xcNbpAqakcM0ftUmFAAIBE81IqBJdS3lS6zs3bIpB9WED3YYXFPmHRfT8sgyrCP1x8uEUxLMzNWElFOYCV6mHWWwMzdPEKHlhLw7NWJqkHc4uIZphavDzA2JPzUDsBZziNae2S6owH8xPmX8G7zzgKEOPUoYHvGz1TBCxMkd3kwNVbU0gKHkx+iZILf77IofhrY1nYFnB/lQPb79drWOyJVa/DAvg9B/rLB4cC+Nqgdz/TvBbBnr6GBReqn/nRmDgaQEej7WhonozjF+Y2I/fZou/qAAAAAElFTkSuQmCC); display:block; height:44px; margin:0 auto -44px; position:relative; top:-22px; width:44px;"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt; &lt;p style=" margin:8px 0 0 0; padding:0 4px;"&gt; &lt;a href="https://www.instagram.com/p/9zYq7DgrY8/" style=" color:#000; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; font-style:normal; font-weight:normal; line-height:17px; text-decoration:none; word-wrap:break-word;" target="_blank"&gt;So Facebook has pretty neat offices.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p style=" color:#c9c8cd; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; line-height:17px; margin-bottom:0; margin-top:8px; overflow:hidden; padding:8px 0 7px; text-align:center; text-overflow:ellipsis; white-space:nowrap;"&gt;A photo posted by Matt (@logicnotlogical) on &lt;time style=" font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; line-height:17px;" datetime="2015-11-07T23:58:54+00:00"&gt;Nov 7, 2015 at 3:58pm PST&lt;/time&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;  

&lt;script async defer src="//platform.instagram.com/en_US/embeds.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In November, nothing really happened again apart from a lot of work and also another hackathon in Nottingham. Enjoy this picture of us hacking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" lang="en"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;6 hours in and hacking is in the air! &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/HackNotts?src=hash"&gt;#HackNotts&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://t.co/Urg8O5rbzd"&gt;pic.twitter.com/Urg8O5rbzd&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; HackNotts (@HackNotts) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/HackNotts/status/670667596430209026"&gt;November 28, 2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;  

&lt;script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh, and since when did the Met Office start picking storm names? At least pick something menacing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" lang="en"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;Stay safe people, watch out for storm &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/Barney?src=hash"&gt;#Barney&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://t.co/gYANvmA1O4"&gt;pic.twitter.com/gYANvmA1O4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Michael Pattinson (@MikePattinson) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/MikePattinson/status/666714160827400192"&gt;November 17, 2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;  

&lt;script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In December, I finally got a haircut.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So yeah, 2016, I'm sorry. You'll probably disappoint me but I won't be mad. 2015 is going to be pretty hard to top.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="//twitter.com/mbell_gb"&gt;@mbell_gb&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width="420" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/j1qQuSuQaHY" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>A Quick Guide To My Webdev Workflow</title><description>You don't make an omelette without cracking many, many eggs.</description><link>https://blog.mbell.me/a-quick-guide-to-my-webdev-workflow/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">1b7ef4d6-9551-4c3a-808d-abad451dab71</guid><category>Programming</category><category>web dev</category><category>node.js</category><dc:creator>Matthew Bell</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 23 Dec 2015 19:29:52 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="https://blog.mbell.me/content/images/2016/06/IMG_20160214_244445150.jpg" medium="image"/><content:encoded>&lt;img src="https://blog.mbell.me/content/images/2016/06/IMG_20160214_244445150.jpg" alt="A Quick Guide To My Webdev Workflow"&gt;&lt;p&gt;So, a couple of people have been asking me about this site and the tools I've been using to get this site to work and to modify it. So here's a quick tour of my workflow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="systemoverview"&gt;System Overview&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I've rented a virtual private server (VPS) from &lt;a href="//digitalocean.com"&gt;Digital Ocean&lt;/a&gt;, which is essentially a virtual machine that has been given its own IP address. I chose DO mainly because I had platform credit, as well as the fact that it was very much "no-frills" and I could just get a virtual machine up and running in a couple of minutes. Also, the fact that the IP is static means that it's perfect for me to set up a small little webserver of my own. Of course, this simplicity comes at the cost of the user having to set up their own security -- the simplest thing is to set up a firewall and to block root access from SSH (or to use key authentication).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The VPS runs server software called &lt;code&gt;nginx&lt;/code&gt;. However, I'm not using this for running the server! I actually use this to act as a reverse proxy, checking for the domain name the incoming HTTP requests are for and forwarding the request to an internal port (this blog is actually hosted on &lt;code&gt;127.0.0.1:2368&lt;/code&gt; if I recall correctly. The same thing goes for my home page, which runs on Node.js. More on this later. I use the program &lt;code&gt;forever&lt;/code&gt; to make my servers run in the background and to restart if crashed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="theblog"&gt;The Blog&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This blog is running on an open-source platform called &lt;a href="//ghost.org"&gt;Ghost&lt;/a&gt;. As well as being a blogging service similar to Tumblr or Medium, Ghost provides the source code for the blog platform which means that you can host it yourself if you have the means. I have done that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other thing you may notice is the green padlock in your browser. This is because I have set up an SSL certificate for this site (a &lt;em&gt;signed&lt;/em&gt; one at that!), which means that your connection to this site is encrypted. Ghost uses log in credentials, so I didn't really want to send that over the internet in plaintext. The service I'm using is &lt;a href="https://letsencrypt.org/"&gt;Let's Encrypt&lt;/a&gt;, which is free but the certificate is only valid for 90 days. So I set up a cronjob to renew it automatically.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="thehomepage"&gt;The Homepage&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My homepage is located at the domain name &lt;a href="//matthewb.me"&gt;matthewb.me&lt;/a&gt;. As previously mentioned, this runs on Node.js, and I'm using Express.js to serve up static files and also to route users if I create an API in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The page itself is just written in plain HTML, along with jQuery for dynamic elements and CSS for the styling. However, standard CSS is not good enough for me so I use a preprocessor called &lt;a href="//sass-lang.com"&gt;Sass&lt;/a&gt;. Sass extends standard CSS by allowing things like variables, functions and also nesting of CSS stanzas which makes things a lot easier for me. Finally, I have set up a git repository on my VPS which means that I can push changes from my computer to the server to update it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, if every time I update the site, I need to possibly update Node.js modules, compile the Sass markup and also restart the server, this would make things a lot more difficult. So, to deal with this, I have set up a git 'post-receive' hook, which is a script that runs after I push a new commit. It looks a bit like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;#!/bin/sh

git --work-tree=/path/to/webserver --git-dir=/path/to/git/repo.git checkout -f  
(cd /path/to/webserver &amp;amp;&amp;amp; npm install &amp;amp;&amp;amp; bower install &amp;amp;&amp;amp; gulp sass)
forever restart --sourceDir /path/to/webserver server.js &amp;gt;&amp;gt; /path/to/webserver/log.txt 2&amp;gt;&amp;amp;1  
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what this does is that it will install new node modules (if there are any in &lt;code&gt;package.json&lt;/code&gt;, update any new bower components if there is any, and run a &lt;a href="http://gulpjs.com/"&gt;Gulp&lt;/a&gt; script that compiles the Sass files. What is Gulp, you ask? It's a way of running build scripts really easily, and it seems like I'm only scratching the ice with what you can do with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, there we have it. If you want some example scripts or some further clarification, don't hesitate to give me a shout!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="//twitter.com/mbell_gb"&gt;@mbell_gb&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>This Blog Platform Is 2Spooky4Me</title><description>Hello from the other side. The wonderful, VPS side.</description><link>https://blog.mbell.me/this-blog-platform-is-2spooky4me/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">867c5706-12e6-4a97-a0c3-aa0f68beca60</guid><category>blog</category><category>Meta</category><dc:creator>Matthew Bell</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 19 Dec 2015 01:18:04 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;So, you're reading this from my newly-hosted blog! I'm running the Ghost CMS on a Digital Ocean droplet, along with my main site, which will be running on node.js. So, what's so good about the change?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="nodependenceontumblr"&gt;No dependence on Tumblr.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I'm now completely self hosted. Although it's not a dedicated server for myself, it &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; a VPS (virtual private server) which is basically a virtual machine spun up just for me. My IP address is static too, so it's perfect for hosting a website. Since my domain registrar is independent, I can easily just copy the domain name to my new servers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="sslencryption"&gt;SSL Encryption!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of some student offer, I bagged myself a free year DV certificate, which you can see is being used on this subdomain. Sadly it can't be used across my subdomains (that costs extra apparently), but I'm using it for the important bits, which is mainly my admin page for this blog.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="itsanicereditor"&gt;It's a nicer editor.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No seriously, check this out:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://blog.mbell.me/content/images/2016/06/2015-12-19_011044_scrot.png" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sweet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="duhitsbuiltonnodejs"&gt;Duh, it's built on Node.js.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I mean, that's half the reason I picked it in the first place. It's open source and I love it. Cheers devs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://twitter.com/mbell_gb"&gt;@mbell_gb&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>"Whack-A-Mole" Pseudocode</title><description>&lt;p&gt;Here’s the pseudocode for my solution to the coursework “whack-a-mole” assignment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;define a state as:
  a 4x4 grid containing none or more moles,
  a list describing the steps to get to this state.

define enqueue(E,Q) as:
  adding the element E to the queue Q.

define dequeue(Q)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;</description><link>https://blog.mbell.me/whack-a-mole-pseudocode/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">dac79788-dde9-4405-a1ac-0c33b5c79238</guid><category>Computer Science</category><category>Programming</category><category>Comp102P</category><dc:creator>Matthew Bell</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 19 Nov 2015 20:17:35 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="https://blog.mbell.me/content/images/2016/06/2015-12-11_212129_scrot.png" medium="image"/><content:encoded>&lt;img src="https://blog.mbell.me/content/images/2016/06/2015-12-11_212129_scrot.png" alt=""Whack-A-Mole" Pseudocode"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here’s the pseudocode for my solution to the coursework “whack-a-mole” assignment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;define a state as:
  a 4x4 grid containing none or more moles,
  a list describing the steps to get to this state.

define enqueue(E,Q) as:
  adding the element E to the queue Q.

define dequeue(Q) as:
  obtaining the element from the front of the queue Q.

create empty queue Q

enqueue(initial state, Q)

while Q is not empty:

  S &amp;lt;- dequeue(Q)

  if the grid stored in S is empty:
    print the steps to get to S from initial state
  else:

    for each mole M in the grid stored in S:
      create a new state S' where M has been hit
      add the mole to the steps of S'
      enqueue S'&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EDIT: Oh look how nice I am, adding a &lt;a href="https://gist.github.com/logicnotlogical/323bc36cb97492e8d2fa#file-whack-a-mole"&gt;C implementation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item></channel></rss>